Finding Aid for Herbert F. Taggart papers, 1934-1980
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Herbert F. Taggart papers 1934-1980
Taggart, Herbert F. (Herbert Francis), 1898-
85407 Aa 2
Professor of accounting in the School of Business Administration of the University of Michigan. Files relating to his testimony and writings on cost accounting cases tried before the Federal Trade Commission under the provisions of the Robinson-Patman Price Discrimination Act; also miscellaneous accounting reports, articles and studies.
4 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was received from Dr. Taggart’s son (donor no. 5465 ) in July 1983.
Periodic additions to the records are not expected.
The collection is open to research.
Herbert F. Taggart was born in Elk Point, South Dakota. He received his B.A., M.B.A., and Ph.D. from the University of Michigan, and joined the faculty of the School of Business Administration in 1920. Dr. Taggart was Chief of the Cost Accounting Unit of the Research and Planning Division of the National Recovery Administration from 1933 to 1935, and in later years served as a consultant to various government agencies.
The papers, 1934-1980, of Herbert F. Taggart have been arranged in alphabetical order by series name. These are Federal Trade Commission, Governor's Commission on Prepaid Hospital and Medical Care Plans; Journal Articles, and Miscellaneous.
Subjects:
Cost accounting.; United States. Federal Trade Commission.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. School of Business Administration.
- Federal Trade Commission 1940-1980
  The largest series in the collection relates to Taggart's work with the Federal Trade Commission, primarily as it concerned the enforcement of the Federal Anti-Price Discrimination Act (Robinson-Patman Act). This act, passed in 1936, was aimed mainly at chain stores that engaged in interstate commerce. As written, the Act made unreasonably low prices tending to destroy competition illegal and empowered the Federal Trade commission to abolish price discrimination that tended to promote monopoly or to restrict competition. Included in Taggart's papers are correspondence, background material, articles, and a Cost Justification Report prepared by the Advisory Committee on Cost Justification. There are also case files relating to the cost accounting cases tried before the Federal Trade Commission under the provisions of the Robinson-Patman Act. As cases were often in litigation over a period of several years, the files include material from the passage of the act through the 19601s. Taggart was called on to testify as an expert cost accountant, and, while some files are more complete than others, they generally contain correspondence, legal papers such as briefs and depositions, transcripts of testimony, and Taggart's later writings on the various cases and cost accounting principles.
  - Advisory opinions (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - Lundvall, A.E. (Box 1)
    - Peloubet, Maurice (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Robinson-Patman Price Discrimination Act
    - Advisory Committee on Cost Justification, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Articles, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Cases
      - Admiral Corporation (Box 1)
      - American Metal Products, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Borden Company, 4 folders (Box 1)
      - Callaway Mills, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Cannon Mills, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Champion Spark Plug (Box 1)
      - Chemway Corporation (Box 1)
      - Crown Zellerbach Corporation, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - General Motors California Case (Box 2)
      - Goodrich, B.F. Company (Box 2)
      - Goodyear Tire and Rubber Company (Box 2)
      - Hood, H.P. and Sons, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - International Salt Company (Box 2)
      - Minneapolis-Honeywell Regulator Company (Box 2)
      - Morton Salt Company (Box 2)
      - Muller, E.B. and Company (Box 2)
      - Niehoff, C.E. and Company (Box 2)
      - Philadelphia Carpet Company (Box 2)
      - Pittsburgh Plate Glass Company (Box 2)
      - Polk, R.L. and Company, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Purolator Products (Box 2)
      - Reid, Edwin M. (College Book Exchange) (Box 2)
      - Russellville Canning Company, 3 folders (Box 2)
      - Simplicity Pattern Company (Box 2)
      - Sperry Rand Corporation (Box 2)
      - Standard Brands, Incorporated (Box 2)
      - Standard Motor Products, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Standard Oil Company, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Sylvania Electric Products, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Thomasville Chair Company (Box 3)
      - Thompson Products, Incorporated, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Transcontinental and Western Air, Incorporated (Box 3)
      - Whirlpool Corporation, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Wilson Foods Corporation, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Miscellaneous Notes (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
    - News Releases and Clippings (Box 3)
    - Patman Committee (Box 3)
- Governor's Commission on Prepaid Hospital and Medical Care Plans
  The Governor's Commission on Prepaid Hospital and Medical Care Plans consists of reports prepared for and by the Commission.
  - Report of the Commission 1962 (Box 4)
  - Report to the Commission by Michigan Hospital Service (Box 4)
  - Study of Hospital and Medical Economics (Box 4)
- Miscellaneous
  The Miscellaneous series includes journal articles, three files of National Recovery Administration papers, including a few items of correspondence, clippings, and a proposed accounting method for the retail farm equipment trade written by Taggart, and studies on Financial and Operating Characteristics of Automobile Dealers and the Franchise System, 1971, and Gasoline Retailing Costs, Detroit and Wayne County, 1939.
  - Journal Articles
    - Journal of Accountancy
      - 1953 Troubles Arising When Government Agencies Fix Accounting Roles (Box 4)
      - 1956 Cost Justification for the Federal Trade Commission (Box 4)
      - 1958 Cost Justification: Rules of the Game (Box 4)
    - Michigan Manufacturer and Financial Record (Box 4)
  - National Recovery Administration 1933-1934
    - John R. Hall Corporation (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
    - Retail Farm Equipment (Box 4)
  - Studies
    - Financial and Operating Characteristics of Automobile Dealers and the Franchise System 1971 (Box 4)
    - Gasoline Retailing Costs, Detroit and Wayne County 1939 (Box 4)
  - Terminology (Unearned Surplus) (Box 4)